#### **DAREK MIHOCKA**

14150 N.E. 20<sup>th</sup> Street, Suite 302 Bellevue, WA 98007-3700 email: <u>darek@emulators.com</u>

#### **SUMMARY**

Over 30 years of low-level development experience with multiple platforms – CPU simulators, compilers, reverse engineering of hardware, emulating legacy computers, and performance tuning. I blog, lecture, and publish conference papers about new CPU architectures, techniques for implementing fast emulators, and arguing the case for interpretation and binary translation based VMs. I have 7 U.S. patents granted to date at Microsoft, Intel, and Amazon related to emulation and virtulization. I developed the world's only commercial Apple Macintosh emulator for Windows PCs, called SoftMac, almost a decade before Apple themselves made the logical switch to Intel CPUs.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Amazon Web Services, Seattle, WA, 2013 - 2015

- Principal Engineer in AppStream, optimizing the streaming of Windows Direct3D applications from EC2
- Involved in performance analysis on recent Windows 2012 R2 instances and C4 (Xeon-v3 based) instance types
- Maintaining and optimizing the existing Android application streaming product called "Test Drive"
- Design and development of a high-performance ARM/Thumb emulation engine
- Presenting engineering talks on the topics of code optimization for AVX2 and scalable cloud emulation
- Coaching other Principal engineers for the "Principals of Amazon" engineering talks

# Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, 2011 to 2013

- Developer on Visual Studio 2013 C/C++ backend team targetting ARM optimizations and new AVX2 extensions
- Bringup of the native C# compiler backend for the new ".NET Native"
- Redesigned the legacy iDNA instrumentation engine and prototyped a new faster binary translator

## Amazon Web Services, Seattle, WA, 2010 to 2011

- Principal Engineer in EC2 focusing on performance and correctness of Windows instances on the EC2 cloud
- Fixed serious issues relating to interrupt latency, clock drift, device drivers, and Windows guest VM performance
- Shipped two product releases: Windows 2008 R2 guest VM support, and cc2.8xlarge 16-core HPC instance
- Developed techniques and new tools to discover and monitor performance anomalies
- On-site customer engagement and contributing customer-facing documentation to the Amazon EC2 web site
- Co-inventor of U.S. patent #8,935,699 related to virtual machine scheduling and performance

#### Intel Corporation, Redmond, WA and Santa Clara, CA, 2008 to 2010

- First full-time engineer hired into the newly formed Hybrid Parallel Computing group at Intel
- Designed and developed simulation tools for performance analysis and new instruction modelling
- Participated in the hardware/software co-design of future Intel processors and new instruction set extensions
- Co-authored CGO and ISCA conference workshop papers related to the simulation work
- Co-inventor on several patents related to hardware transactional memory

## Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, 2001 to 2008

- Lead developer on "Nirvana", a dynamic recompilation instrumentation framework used by "iDNA"
- Co-authored paper on Nirvana and iDNA Time Travel Debugging technology published at VEE 2006
- Co-inventor on U.S. patent #7,620,938 relating to my work on iDNA Time Travel Debugging technology
- Lead developer on "Helium" Pentium III on 64-bit PowerPC emulation project for Xbox 360
- Co-inventor on U.S. patent #7,752,028 relating to simulation of arithmetic flags on PowerPC processors
- Maintenanced Vulcan and BBT (Microsoft's static code instrumentation and optimization tools)
- Performance tuning ARM code on Windows Phone, PowerPC code on Xbox 360, and x86/x64 code on Windows

Emulators.com, Bellevue, WA, 1997 to 2001 full time, ongoing hobby from 1988 to present

- Founded company to provide products related to Macintosh-PC cross-platform operability
- Designed, developed, and shipped the "SoftMac" Apple Macintosh emulator for Windows in under two years
- Negotiated distribution deals of SoftMac with resellers in Japan, Europe, and North America
- Managed and coordinated company exhibits at Macworld, Comdex, PC Expo, and CeBIT trade shows
- Customers include Microsoft, Honeywell, various school boards, and thousands of Apple and Atari end-users
- Blogger since 2000, helping PC users with their problems, posting hardware reviews and industry analysis
- Released much of our code as open source, and contributed to open source projects such as "Bochs" x86 emulator

Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, 1990 to 1997

- Full-time SDE in the Applications and Languages Divisions, focusing on performance issues and code quality
- Contributed to Visual C++ 4.x and 5.0 back end code generation optimizations producing 10% smaller code
- Design and developed the PowerPC P-code VM and bytecode instruction set used for Mac Office 98
- Boot-time and performance optimization work on Office 95, Office 97, Mac Office 98
- Also worked on Works for Windows 2.0, PC Works 3.0, POSIX runtimes in NT, and MASM for PowerPC

Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, 1987, 1989

- Three-time intern in the Applications Division on projects such as Multiplan for OS/2 and PowerPoint 2.0
- Used cross-platform development tools hosted on XENIX/386 and OS/2

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ont., 1985 to 1990

- B.A. in Computer Engineering co-op program
- Awarded Engineering Faculty Special Entrance Scholarship (one of top 8 scholarships awarded per year)
- Ranked in top 16 students nationwide in various Canadian math and physics high school contests

#### **SKILLS AND INTERESTS**

- Proficient in C/C++ as well as x86/AMD64/Intel64, PowerPC, 680x0, 6502, and ARM assembly languages
- Windows NT/XP/7/8, Windows 9x, MS-DOS, Mac OS, GEM/TOS, Fedora, RHEL, and Ubuntu operating systems
- Strong interests in mathematics, physics, electronics, and microprocessor architecture
- Experienced with public presentations, press interviews on television, radio, and magazines
- Authored several computer magazine articles since 1985, online hardware reviews, and years of blogging
- Open source contributions, including significant optimizations to the Bochs x86 simulator

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

"How Bochs Works", June 2012

http://bochs.sourceforge.net/How%20the%20Bochs%20works%20under%20the%20hood%202nd%20edition.pdf

"Fast Microcode Interpretation with Transactional Commit/Abort", AMAS-BT workshop at ISCA, San Jose, June 2011 http://www.emulators.com/docs/amas-bt2011.pdf

"Proposal for Hardware-Assisted Arithmetic Overflow Detection", WISH workshop at CGO, Toronto, April 2010 <a href="http://www.emulators.com/docs/LazyOverflowDetect">http://www.emulators.com/docs/LazyOverflowDetect</a> Final.pdf

"Virtualization without Direct Execution", AMAS-BT workshop at ISCA 2008, Beijing, June 2008 <a href="http://www.emulators.com/docs/VirtNoJit Paper.pdf">http://www.emulators.com/docs/VirtNoJit Paper.pdf</a>

"Framework for Instruction-level Tracing and Analysis", VEE 2006, Ottawa, June 2006 <a href="http://www.usenix.org/events/vee06/full">http://www.usenix.org/events/vee06/full</a> papers/p154-bhansali.pdf